<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>News | Your Data Science Mentor - Mohsen Davarynejad</title>
    <link>https://dataqubed.io/news/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://dataqubed.io/news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>News</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://dataqubed.io/media/icon_hu7729264130191091259.png</url>
      <title>News</title>
      <link>https://dataqubed.io/news/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Returning to My Roots - Embracing the Joys of Academic Life</title>
      <link>https://dataqubed.io/news/teach-courses/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dataqubed.io/news/teach-courses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve got some good news to share!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After spending around 10 years in the industry, I&amp;rsquo;m happy to be back in the academic world. It turns out, I missed the joy of never-ending coffee and brainstorming sessions next to writing proposals, and scientific articles as well as serving as a reviewer of journals and conferences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And wow, I did miss it! I don&amp;rsquo;t regret a single moment of my time in the industry, but I do wonder why it took me so long to realize what truly drives and excites me. I guess you could say it was my &lt;code&gt;Eureka!&lt;/code&gt; moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve joined Breda University of Applied Sciences as a Faculty lecturer in &lt;code&gt;data_science&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;machine_learning&lt;/code&gt;, and it’s been incredibly rewarding so far. Plus, I get to throw around terms like machine learning, data science and &lt;code&gt;AI&lt;/code&gt; even more and look really hashtag#smart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A huge shoutout to all my amazing colleagues in the industry especially folks at Basic-Fit, KLM Royal Dutch Airlines, Randstad, Capgemini, Philips, Shell. Let’s stay in touch! You never know when I might need a break from grading students and want to hear some good hashtag#gossip next to finding common group projects to collaborate on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to collaboration, not only with former colleagues from the academic world but also with new, enriching, and perhaps even quirky connections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;#NewBeginnings&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;#AcademicLife&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;#DataScience&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;#MachineLearning&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;#FeelingGrateful&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you Breda University of Applied Sciences!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
